Finding Aid for Pediatric Nurse Practitioner Program (University of Michigan) records, 1972-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Pediatric Nurse Practitioner Program (University of Michigan) records 1972-1979
University of Michigan. Pediatric Nurse Practitioner Program.
1 linear foot
87279 Bimu C266 2
Project of the University of Michigan School of Nursing and the Department of Health, Education and Welfare, includes grant proposals, reports, course materials, and scattered conference files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated by Barbara Sachs in September 1984 (Donor no. 7100 ).
NO further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Pediatric Nurse Practitioner Program (PNP) was jointly initiated by the School of Nursing, the Department of Continuing Education for Nurses, and the Medical School's Department of Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases, in August 1973. It was begun at the request of the Michigan Department of Public Health's Bureau of Maternal Child Health in order to relieve practicing pediatricians of many primary health care responsibilities. A thirty-two week undergraduate credit program was developed leading to a special certificate. Barbara Sachs, who served as nurse co-director, devoted most of her time to the operation of the program. Between 1974 and 1977 the program was funded through a grant from the Division of Nursing, Department of Health, Education and Welfare. In 1979 the existence of eight to ten similar programs, a difficulty in placing program participants in clinical settings, staffing problems and other reasons led the School of Nursing to revamp the PNP, making it a part of the School's graduate degree program. This change, however, did not resolve difficulties experienced within the PNP and in August 1980 the program was ended.
Records of the PNP consist of one linear foot of material, dating from 1972 to 1979. Included are the HEW grant proposal, various supplemental grant reports as well as the final report, some course materials, and a partial explanation for the eventual termination of the program.
Subjects:
Nurses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Pediatric nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.; University of Michigan. Pediatric Nurse Practitioner Program.
- Topical Files
  - Annual Report, 1976-197 (Box 1)
  - Comparative Data, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Conferences
    - "Changing Roles and Relationships for Health Professionals," March 27, 1974 (Box 1)
    - "Innovators in Nursing of Children" November 7, 1975 (Box 1)
    - "Rights of Children", November 5, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Closure Decision, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Consultant Report, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Course Material
    - Evaluation Plan (Box 1)
    - Maslow's Theory of Motivation (Box 1)
    - Study Questions/reading Lists (Box 1)
    - Trends in Expanding Nursing Roles (Box 1)
  - Proposal (Original) N01 NU 34059 1972 (Box 1)
  - Reports to Department of Health, Education and Welfare
    - Final, (1974-1977) submitted September 1, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Interim (Box 1)
  - Syllabus
    - 1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976 Winter (Box 1)